Mss.Rec.4 Mss.Rec.4
American Philosophical Society
Delaware Indian material
1928
Mss.Rec.4
American Philosophical Society
2.0 Tape(s)
Songs performed by Chief James Webber (Witapano'xwe,) May 10, 1928. Originally recorded on wax cylinders, dubbed to sound tape reels in 1950. Included are dance songs, peyote songs, women's social dance songs (with Shawnee and Iroquois versions), a speech, portions of a big house ceremony, and songs for First Day.
2 sound tape reels (41 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, 1 track, mono; 7 in. The contents of this collection were originally recorded on wax cylinders by Frank G. Speck in 1928 and later copied to sound tape reels circa 1950.
Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
Webber, James C.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Mrs. Frank G. Speck and accessioned, 1950.
General note
There are transcriptions available at the repository [497.3/Am4 #84].
Biographical/Historical note
Frank Gouldsmith Speck was an anthropologist.
Delaware Indians--Music; Delaware Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Indians of North America; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Pleasure Dance #1, 1928; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:27; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Scope and Contents note
    Women's stomp dance. May be a women's side dance in which women dance while men sing. Possibly a Shawnee song sung in Delaware. Playback speed uneven due to condition of the original cylinder.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Cylinder recording) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Delaware dance; Delaware Indians--Music; Philadelphia (Pa.); Shawnee Indians--Music; Stomp dance
  - Pleasure Dance #2, 1928; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:26; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Women's stomp dance. May be a women's side dance in which women dance while men sing. Possibly a Seneca song sung in Delaware. Playback speed uneven due to condition of the original cylinder.
    Delaware dance; Delaware Indians--Music; Philadelphia (Pa.); Seneca Indians--Music; Stomp dance
  - Pleasure Dance #3, 1928; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:15; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Women's stomp dance. May be a women's side dance in which women dance while men sing. Playback speed uneven due to condition of the original cylinder.
    Delaware dance; Delaware Indians--Music; Philadelphia (Pa.); Stomp dance
  - Pleasure Dance #4, 1928; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:33; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Women's stomp dance. May be a song where women stop dancing and sing together with the men singers. Program ends with summary given by Frank Speck of this and the three preceding Pleasure Dance songs. Playback speed uneven due to condition of the original cylinder.
  - Delaware Peyote Song, 1928; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:16; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Delaware Indians--Music; Peyote songs; Philadelphia (Pa.)
  - Fragment of Big House vision recital, with song, 1928; 01-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:20; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Program contains significant, sometimes loud sound distortions and skipping due to poor condition of original cylinder.
    Big House Ceremony (Delaware rite); Delaware Indians--Music; Delaware Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Peyote songs; Philadelphia (Pa.)
  - Woman's Dance Song used in Morning of Big House, describing her vision of a mermaid, 1928; 01-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:55; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Identified by Ives Goddard (see Related Resource) as a woman's vision-recital song. According to Speck's documentation the song is "sung by J. Webber as his grandmother's song. She was Mawatdes 'Bundle in Good Shape' She died 1912, at age 109 years." Goddard alternately translates Mawatdes as of Munsee origin, meaning "One-Who-Has-No-Food." Speck's introduces the recording: "This is the song of Mawatdes, one of the oldest living women that the Delaware and Munsee tribes had. [She] died at the age of 109 years old, according to the scripture(?) as it was calculated from the place she gives of her birth. Her song follows." May contain some terms of Munsee origin.
    Delaware Indians--Music; Philadelphia (Pa.)
  - Woman's Dance Song, 1928; 01-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:38; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Women's stomp dance song. Words given by Speck as "cwahakwiyus... 'white man meat' or 'stale meat.'" Words given by Goddard (see Related Resource) as "šuwánakw wiyóshe," meaning "'whiteman is making meat'; better 'the whiteman has meat'?...or 'hunts meat'?"
  - Woman's Dance Song, ywietani-ke, "dancing nicely", 1928; 01-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:48; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Women's stomp dance song. Words possibly in Seneca. Song may be of Shawnee origin.
  - Witapanoxwe's Song, 1928; 01-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:47; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Vision recital song, or atehomwin song, of James C. Webber, whose Delaware name is Witapano'xwe. Song may be of Seneca or Shawnee origin. Contains some Munsee terms.
    Delaware Indians--Music; Philadelphia (Pa.); Seneca Indians--Music; Shawnee Indians--Music
  - Atehomwin Song of Kanipaxoxwe, 1928; 01-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:02; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Vision recital song, or atehomwin song, of Joe Washington, whose Delaware name is Kanipaxoxwe. Sung by James C. Webber.
  - Woman's Dance Songs (not used in Big House) - Delaware, Shawnee, and Iroquois versions, 1928-05-10; 01-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:17; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Delaware dance; Delaware Indians--Music; Iroquois dance; Philadelphia (Pa.); Shawnee dance; Stomp dance
  - Short address by Chief Webber in Delaware (broken off), 1928-05-10; 01-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:35; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Delaware Indians--History; Philadelphia (Pa.); Speeches, addresses, etc., Delaware
  - Short address in Delaware by Chief Webber, 1928-05-10; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:01; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
  - Witapano'xwe's Big House vision recital and song, 1928; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:05; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Big House ceremony vision recital and song of James C. Webber, whose Delaware name is Witapano'xwe.
  - Witapano'xwe's Big House vision recital and song, 1928; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:53; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
  - Delaware Dance Songs (not used in Big House): a: Raccoon Dance, 1928; 02-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:22; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
  - Delaware Dance Songs (not used in Big House): c: Women's Dance, 1928; 02-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:12; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Identified by Goddard (see Related Resource) as a Raccoon Dance, possibly Shawnee in origin.
  - Delaware Dance Songs (not used in Big House): d: Women's Dance, 1928; 02-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:13; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
  - Delaware Song A - song to go with Big House Ceremony, Song of Leader (Elkhair) as he opens the Ceremony the First Day, 1928-03-10; 02-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:34; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Webber, James C.
    Identified by Goddard (see Related Resource) as "Charley Elkhair's Big House vision recital and song" Program contains severe background noise due to poor condition of original cylinder.